Stanford
University so the goal of today was to
show
you how a particle like the photon a
particle like the photon can gain a mass
can get a mass from something called
spontaneous symmetry
breaking uh how it can gain a mass from
some called the higs phenomenon two
important ingredients that I haven't
emphasized tonight both of them
technical but also one of them more
technical than the other one of them
called spontaneous symetry breaking and
the other called gaug in variants we
have to go through them if we really
want to seriously understand what's
going on their mathematical
ideas and so we can't avoid
mathematics as
usual last time I think I discussed a
little bit an example of spontaneous
symmetry breaking namely a very simple
model of magnets where the magnets
little magnets individual magnets can
either point up or down and when the
energy is such that the energy is lower
when they're parallel either this way or
this way and larger if they're
anti-parallel
parallel there is no fundamental
asymmetry between up and
down two neighboring up uh little
magnets have the same energy as two
neighboring down magnets one up and one
down has the same energy as one down and
one up so there's no fundamental
difference between up up and
down but
nevertheless because the spins are en
because it's energetically favorable for
them to be parallel then all you have to
do is go very very far away let's let's
imagine now we're talking about the
ground state the state of lowest energy
this magnet has been frozen all its
energy sucked out of it which state is
it in you can think of two possibilities
they could all be up or they could all
be down one up and one down anywhere as
will cost more energy but which is it
are they all up or are they all down
well the answer is is determined by one
spin very very far away you go very very
far
away and you freeze one of them just one
spin very very far away the effect will
be that its neighbors in order to save
energy we want to be parallel to it all
right so let's say the four or the six
neighbors around it depending on the
dimension of space in three dimensions
there are six Neighbors on a square lat
on a cubic lattice so it will will tell
its neighbors look you want to save
energy point the same way I point but
then the six neighbors have a bunch of
neighbors connected to them and so forth
and so on and the effect will be that
the that the entire lattice if we really
want to be in the ground state will'll
all point in One
Direction uh
so there is a symmetry but the Symmetry
is spontaneously broken now let's let's
just distinguish that and compare it
with what I will call explicit symmetry
breaking explicit symmetry breaking is
different imagine that in instead a
slightly different system perhaps the
same system but one added ingredient
there's a magnetic field and the
magnetic field points
up in that
case the just an individual spin one
spin at a time forget its neighbors will
per prefer to point along the direction
of the magnetic field prefer what does
that mean it means the energy will be
lower when it's pointing along the
magnetic
field this is an explicit breaking
there's something in the system which is
single down up as different than
down the expression for the energy is no
longer symmetric if all I had was one
spin the energy would be different if it
were up and down and in that case it
really does doesn't matter what you do
very very far away doesn't make much
difference um there's an enormous
Savings of energy if all of the spins
are pointing along the magnetic
field if you try to take a substantial
number of them and flip them in the
wrong direction the energy cost would be
enormous it would be proportional to the
total number of spins that you try to
change so one spin far away holding it
in some direction is not going to have
much influence uence far
away why because if it did have an
influence far away and lines things up
with it the cost in energy would be
enormous so that's explicit symmetry
breaking yeah does a particle with no
charge but spin have a preferred
orientation in magnetic field uh we can
it has a magnetic they have magnetic
moments no charge but magnetic moments
right by mean like the neutron neutron
as a Magnetic Moment but no
charge but spontaneous you mean they
would all flip at the same time or would
they propagate out well that's a good
question I mean in the real world they
propagate out
yeah yeah if you uh that's a good
question if you had all the spins lined
up in one way the wrong in some way and
then you spontaneous case and you came
and you flipped one of the spins and
held it down yes a wave would go out uh
just like stack Domino
H just like stacko yeah yeah mhm except
in three
dimensions you have multiple waves
basically moving through a material a
typical case would you you would have
multiple waves moving through a large
material at any given point from
multiple distant influencers affecting
different we're going to talk about
waves uh waves uh of re you mean waves
of reorientation yeah we're going to
talk extensively about waves of re
orientation uh
but okay so question how would you know
you find one of these magnetic systems
not a real magnet it's just a
mathematical model with spins which can
either be up or down you find a sample
and it's all pointing up right you want
to find out whether it's spontaneous
symmetry breaking or let's call it
explicit symmetry breaking
what's the difference what are there any
phenomena which are characteristic of
One Versus the
other the answer is yes in the case of
the simple magnets which can either be
up or down the special phenomenon
associated with the spontaneous symmetry
breaking is the existence of domain
walls what is a domain wall if you had a
big
sample there's a big sample
here
and
you decided to do an experiment there a
finite size sample but very big so you
go out to the boundaries let's say the
left boundary and you make all the spins
up you just freeze them you hold on to
them perhaps by putting the the spins on
the boundary over here this is
incidentally this is not time two space
directions just for Simplicity you
freeze all of the spins up Ward over
here what do you expect to happen well
of course the system will save energy by
filling itself up with all up spins
parallel spins not because there's
anything around here which is favoring
up spins but just because each neighbor
influences its all its neighbors and
says you'll save energy if you're up
okay uh how do you tell the difference
between that an explicit symmetry
breaking which is the which is the
presence of a magnetic field
field in the bulk of this sample here
orienting the spins up well one
experiment you could do is you could go
over to this side over
here and place all of the spins
down then what do you expect in the two
cases in the two cases you expect quite
different Behavior If there really was a
preference an explicit symmetry breaking
that said you save energy by being up
then the effect of what's going on over
here would not be very important it
might propagate in a little ways but it
certainly would not flip a large
macroscopic um percentage of the spins
because that just costs energy to turn
them relative to the explicit magnetic
field so if there was a magnetic field
pointing up the effect of turning them
down here would only propagate a little
ways in
and uh would be too costly in energy to
turn over any large macroscopic um
fraction of them on the other hand if up
is just as good as down in other words
if there is nothing external to the
system saying up is preferred then the
effect is quite different instead the uh
the favorable energy
configuration will be one in which half
the sample on one side is
down
and half the sample on the other side is
up now the split might not be at the
center that's not so
important but uh this would be a
perfectly good
configuration where half of them would
be up half of them would be down you
cannot find a state with lower energy
there is no state of lower energy than
half being up and half being
down this would be called The Domain
wall the separation between the two
types of behaviors would be called a
domain wall so for this simple
example the phenomena that would
characterize spontaneous symmetry
breaking would be the existence of
domain walls where on either side of the
domain wall there would
be basically identical things except
reflected by 180° domain walls would be
the the existence of domain
walls would be the signal the signature
of spontaneous symmetry breakdown for
this
case
now um we can think of a a field Theory
which has very similar
behaviors here's a field Theory we have
a field let's just call it
fi is green okay does green work all
right
say it again I think Black is Black is
better all right let's try what I do
with the black here it
is all
right a field fine now for the
Simplicity now fi is a real valued field
only one
component and it can take on any value
any real value from plus infinity to
minus
infinity and there's a Dynamics to this
field which is controlled by a l
grangian let's write a lran for it it's
a relativistic field and
usual expression for the kinetic energy
of a relativistic field is to
differentiate fi with respect to the
direction
mu and square that well you square it
with some uh some signs Plus signs and
minus signs that are characteristic of
Relativity and that we describe by
putting upper and lower indices but
basically this is just the sums actually
differences of squares of the time
derivative squared sorry the the
difference between the time derivative
squared and the space derivative
squared this thing here is 12 5 do^
2ar minus the derivative with respect to
X of 5^ 2 same thing for y and so forth
and z and we'll just represent that by d
mufi d mui we could even represent it
more simply let's even represent it by a
an even uh simpler notation let's just
call it 1/2 and the 1 half is
completely um conventional meaning to
say it's a convention but you could
change it it wouldn't make any
difference to the
physics uh simple notation would just be
to write defy squared and it means 5 do^
2 minus gradient to 5^ 2 and then you
can add another term which is a
potential energy a potential
energy uh minus V of fi minus a
potential which depends on fi potential
energy it doesn't depend on the
gradients of fi the time derivative is a
space derivative it just depends on fi
itself and imagine that V of fi looks
something like
this completely symmetric exactly
symmetric with respect to changing
plus to minus all right so here would be
5al 0 right over here let's call this
point 5 = F and here F = minus f plus F
and minus F and plus F and minus f are
completely symmetric this function
assume it is completely symmetric with
respect to flipping about the vertical
axis and under that case there will once
again be two
ground states of the field two states of
lowest energy incidentally the energy
has a plus sign for V ofi the lran has a
minus the energy has a plus sign there
will be two states in one configuration
the field will sit at this point over
here everywhere is in
space so everywhere is in our sample or
in space f could be minus
F now why why can't it make a jump
obviously the energy is lowest if fi is
at this value or this value but why
can't it jump from here to here without
a big cost in
energy energy time is greater than
clanks constant or
something well supposing supposing the
field just went the just a sharp
boundary here f = f f = minus f
everywhere is in this sample V is equal
to either plus or minus F and so this
potential energy here is
minimized but what about the derivative
energies
here what about the terms in the energy
proportional to let's say the derivative
of f with respect to x^ squared this
direction could be
X then there's a huge jump or a very
sudden jump and fi going from here to
here a sudden jump means a large
derivative in fact if the jump was
sudden meaning really concentrated the
derivative of five would be very big the
square of it would be even bigger and
you would pay a large price in energy
for a sudden
jump okay on the other hand you pay no
price if f is either equal to F or or
minus F everywhere is this is very much
like the magnets lined
up uh that um and again is a case of
spontaneous symmetry
breaking a different possibility where
there would be no spontaneous symmetry
breaking would be if the potential
energy instead looked like
this then the ground state would just be
f equals
z
well FAL
0 is the same as 5al minus
0 and there would be no bias uh you
would not observe anything in here you
would just have pi equals Zer
everywhere and there would be
no breaking of the symmetry of left to
right or of plus 5 to
minus5 okay so that uh that would be the
case of a spontaneous this would be the
spontaneously broken case this would be
the unbroken case in one case the ground
state simply has the field equal to zero
in the other case there are two ground
States two identical ground well
physically identical ground States and
again in this case here if you insisted
that the field was plus F on this end
and minus F on this end by you know
going into the system and holding it
down then there would be a transition
somewhere in the
middle from minus F to plus f it would
be costly in energy because of these
gradient terms but still you have no
choice you said it's Plus on this end
minus on this end and there would be a
domain wall down the down the center
yeah so are you assuming that there's no
influence from the second nearest
neighbors only the nearest neighbors no
we're not assuming that so why wouldn't
everything just be random everything up
and down up and down everywhere because
if you look at the secondary nearest
neighbors right they would be in the
same orientation as the as long as the
second nearest neighbor interactions
also preferred parallel this it wouldn't
make much
difference if you had a situation where
the first nearest neighbors preferred
parallel and the second nearest
neighbors anti-parallel you might get
into some kind of
competition yeah that term spontaneous
that to
no it
refers to the idea that there's really
no fundamental
asymmetry it there a question of chance
which way it goes or if not chance that
you can you can set off the difference
by a very very tiny perturbation very
tiny perturbation just one
spin it is a kind of instability it's a
kind of instability that uh that what
does an instability mean an instability
means that a very very small
perturbation on a system will change it
a lot all right so small in this case
may may mean that just one spin far away
is being tampered with you would
ordinarily think that's not much of a
change in a system you go far you have a
system which is a million zillion miles
by a million million zillion
miles and it's loaded up with a a huge
number of these spins and somebody off
on office Cur turns one of them over and
what's the effect the effect is would be
of a propagating wave which would come
in and uh would take some time of course
but which would cause if you sucked all
the energy out of the system would cause
the ground state to be to realign
itself is it is it starting out in one
state and it get flipped to the other or
is it starting out in unknown well it it
depends on the particular physical
situation uh all right we say a little
bit more about it at high temperatures
where there's lots of random
fluctuation it may be and it typically
would be that the random fluctuation
would be such that on the average there
would be equal amounts of up and down
random fluctuation now you start to cool
it you cool it and take energy out of it
and take energy out of it which way is
it going to go well the answer is uh
that it's a sort of a random thing a
patch might form plus over here minus
over here another uh some patchwor might
start to form to lower the energy where
they were parallel and then the patches
would connect themselves together and
the patches would try to align each
other and eventually it's a matter of
random chance which one will take over
the whole
system okay so and that's that's what's
called spontaneous symmetry breaking now
in this case here you could ask what
would correspond to explicit symmetry
breaking anybody guess any enough energy
to put it over the hill no no no no one
lower than the other H one lower than
the other yeah that's right
if if the
potential had an imbalance so that one
was lower than the
other then this would be an explicit
symmetry break Bing and the ground state
would sit here okay so explicit symmetry
baking that means it's something
asymmetric in if you like in the lanan
itself or in the potential energy just
an explicit term in the fundamental
setup to begin with which favors one
side or favors one configuration instead
of the other that's explicit symmetry
breaking in that case if you take a very
very big sample there will not be domain
walls it would be very energetically
unfavorable to have domain walls the
domain wall will simply want to minimize
the number of wrongheaded wrong directed
spins or wrong directed fields and
simply move over and try to wipe out the
wrong spins it might not be able to
completely do it but it won't the domain
wall will not be in the center because
that will require too many spins to be
in the wrong State too many degrees of
freedom too many um points of space to
be wrongly
aligned okay so I think we have the
basic idea of what a spontaneous
symmetry breaking is but now we're going
to talk and in this case the two cases
that I've discussed the symmetry which
is
broken is a discrete symmetry in the
spin case it was spin up goes to spin
down in this case it's left goes to
right it's not a continuous symmetry A
continuous symmetry is one where you can
interpolate in between you can
interpolate continuously in
between uh whatever configurations there
are U1 is a continuous symmetry we'll
discuss it uh in a moment in fact we're
going to discuss it right
now su2 su3 whatever they're all
continuous symmetries where you can
interpolate
configurations by using the continuous
generators of the group to go from one
configuration to
another um the magnetic case real
magnets real magnets often in the real
world have continuous symmetries The
Continuous symmetry would be not just
can you flip a spin but you can rotate a
spin so for
example some examples of
ferromagnets uh real ferromagnets have
continuous symmetries where the spins
prefer to be aligned all right but it's
not just up and down but anywhere in
between right in that case the Symmetry
group is not just reflection but
rotations and it's a continuous group
so we will want since we're interested
in things like su2 and su3 and U1 we
want to understand what it would mean to
spontaneously break a continuous
symmetry I'm going to do one example
tonight of both the notion of continuous
symmetry breaking what the idea of a
gold stone Bon is which replaces domain
walls and
how this can radically change its nature
when the symmetry has to do with Gauge
bons when it has to do with gauge bosons
and morphs from spontaneous symmetry
breaking into the higs
phenomenon in particular how fig higs
phenomena gives particles like the zosan
masses how it provides a mechanism for
them to have
masses so let's uh let's try to go
through that
mathematics all right first of all we're
talking as I said about continuous
symmetries and I don't want to do the
general case it's not interesting for us
at this point to do the general case
let's do a very specific case the
specific case involves a field let's
call it fire
again but f is now a complex field
instead of just existing on the real
axis instead of having a value on the
real axis it has a complex
value or another way of saying it is it
can take on any value in the plane in
the two-dimensional plane what is the
plane the
plane is the plane of the real value of
fi and the imaginary value of fi and the
complex field fi is f
real plus I * F
imaginary and we'll just call it
fi it's a field it depends on
position but knowledge of that field
involves knowledge of the two
independent components of the field now
these components are not components in
space this is just a field which is
composed out of two fields and group
together to form something called the
complex field fi
and of course there's also a canonical
conjugate uh s not a canonical conjugate
a complex conjugate F
star which is just equal to F real minus
i f
imaginary all right so fi is a thing
which lives in the plane like this
meaning to say the values that it takes
on are in a
plane and let's suppose that the
in that case we would write the kinetic
energy here not in this form but as the
product of the derivative of the
conjugate of f * F itself this is
equivalent to the sum of two terms one
involving fi real and the other
involving fi imaginary you can rewrite
this as if you liked you could rewrite
it as D muf real squared plus D mu VI
imaginary squared that's just using the
idea that uh the square of a complex or
the or a complex conjugate a complex
number times its own complex conjugate
is just the product of the real
components or the square of the real
components plus the square of the
imaginary components all right but let's
uh let's write it this way and in fact
the half is normally not put there for
complex
Fields now this this
lran has a symmetry and the Symmetry is
the U1 symmetry let's write it
down
where you replace everywhere is five by
F Prime and F
Prime is
equal to eus I Theta *
5 in other words we multiply the field
at every point does not stand for
derivative here it's just a redefinition
of the field where we multiply it by e
to the I Theta do you know what that
means on the complex plane
here yeah we rotate it by angle
Theta now it's this lunian here does
have that symmetry where at the same
time F Prime
Star is equal to eus I Theta * 5 I
prime did I write that sorry F
star Theta is a constant at the moment
Theta is a constant um constant with
respect to space it could be any
phase but it is not allowed to vary from
point to point or time to time at the
moment okay why why is this invariant
under
that because the e to the I thetas will
cancel out the derivative let's write
down the derivative of f Prime I'm just
I'm not going to write D byd mu I'll
just write derivative abstract
derivative of f Prime is just e to the I
Theta time the derivative of f why
because Theta is constant by
assumption likewise the derivative of f
star Prime F Prime Star is e to the
minus I Theta times the derivative of f
star that means the product of DF Prime
with d star Prime is exactly the same
the e to the I thet is cancel out and so
the lunian is unchanged by rotating the
field by a phase that's called a
symmetry that's what a symmetry means
operations that you can do which don't
change lunian of course I could write
other lunians which don't respect the
symmetry
but what else can we add to the
lran let's get rid of these M's and just
call it derivative of five * derivative
of f star you can remember that there's
some signs in there um you can add a
potential so let's add a potential in
lran that always
means subtracting vfi but I want vfi to
have the same symmetry in other words I
want it to maintain the symmetry under
these phase rotations how do I do that
and the answer is very simple you
require that the potential is a function
only of f star
five in other words it's only a function
of F real squar plus F imaginary
squared say it
again was it was there a question no
okay now it's clear that this lran has
the Symmetry even with the potential
term I could break the Symmetry all
sorts of ways of breaking the Symmetry
if I made the potential a function of
some other combination let's say just fi
Real by itself without fi imaginary that
would break the Symmetry okay what is
the
Symmetry uh from the point of view of
this picture over here it is the
symmetry of rotating the five plane at
every point just take whatever the field
is at any point in space and rot rotate
it here rotate all the fields
simultaneously and that is the Symmetry
that we're talking
about okay let's now focus on two
different kinds of potential energies
one of them spontaneously breaks the
Symmetry the other doesn't the situation
is very very similar to
uh uh to the previous case first of all
as a simple example let's take a
potential well let's let's draw
it oh let's write it let's just take the
potential F star
five five star five where is Five Star
five
minimized that's zero it's it's always
positive except when it's zero and so
the potential is minimum right over
here that point is obviously a symmetric
point with respect to rotating the plane
and so a potential like this where which
I'll draw for you in a minute I mean
I'll show you what we'll draw it in a
minute a potential like that is
symmetric and there is
no either explicit or spontaneous
symmetry breaking associated with it the
ground state is just f equals zero
completely symmetric but now let's write
another
potential uh let's write Min - A * this
plus b * 5 Star
5^ squared
this potential has the property that
near the
origin incidentally near the origin this
is bigger than this when five is small 5
to the 4th this is is like 5 to the 4th
5 to the 4th is much smaller than a 5^
squ so near the origin the potential
energy is not minimum at zero but it's
maximum at
zero it the field doesn't want to be at
zero field doesn't want to to be zero
because it cost more energy for it to be
zero than to move away from zero
potential energy because of the minus
sign here favors having fi move away
from zero on the other hand it doesn't
want to move too far from zero if B is
positive let's suppose B is positive if
B is positive for large fi this is
bigger than this so when this is bigger
than
this uh you don't want to have too much
field because this will get big and
overwhelm this what will happen a
competition between these two will take
place and there will be a favorable
value of five star five at some value we
can draw a picture let's draw a picture
there's a picture of the potential
here's the five plane I'll make the five
plane
horizontal and vertically is the
potential
energy in the first case the first case
was plus and I didn't even write this
here but we could
what does the potential look like it's a
function only of f star five that means
it's a function only of the distance
from the origin and the potential would
look like something like
this it would be a
paraboloid it would be a paraboloid
which would have complete rotational
symmetry
about 5 equal
0 here the energy is minimum here the
potential energy is minimum minimum
that's 5al
0 and if we move away from 5al 0 there's
a symmetry which makes sure that the
potential energy doesn't depend on angle
right that's the character of the first
case where we just had plus a f star F
and in fact we could put in another term
it doesn't matter the only specific
ingredient here is that the potential is
upward and continues to go upward so
that the minimum of energy is right at 5
equal 0 under those circumstances we
would say there's no symmetry breaking
no spontaneous symmetry breaking on the
other hand let's go back to the case
with minus here then the potential looks
like
this it starts out at the
origin and goes
negative until the quartic term becomes
as large as the quadratic term and then
it turns
up it's still symmetric about
rotation I don't it's a little bit hard
to
draw uh it's a surface of
Revolution meaning to say it's symmetric
with respect to rotation about this axis
here and the minimum is not a point but
the minimum lies on a
circle it lies on a circle in the
complex plane from this point of view
over here the minimum energy state is
somewhere
along a circle of a radius which is
determined by the parameters here you
simply minimize this function as a
function of F star F and you find out
where that point is let's call the
radius F that's a standard notation for
it incidentally the minimum of the
potential is not at a point it's along a
track it's sort of along a track like
this but a track of radius
F all right now what is the ground state
of this
system there are many ground States and
they're all of the same energy they
correspond to the field being at any
point along the circle
here
everywhere a way to think about this is
to imagine that
um the field is a bunch of little arrows
not arrows in space arrows in this
abstract
space they want to be aligned along the
same direction how do I know that
because if there's variation in the
field from one point to another then
this term has a lot of energy in it okay
the gradient term so the field wants to
stay parallel in this internal abstract
space the there everywhere is in Space
the field will want to lie at the same
angle
but uh there's an ambiguity which
direction the energy is the same along
any direction as long as the field has
magnitude F in other words as long as
it's stuck in this track here or
equivalently in this track over here
then the energy is
minimum can can you say anything beyond
that no that's it the energy will be
minimum somewhere everywhere along here
okay but it will cost energy to cause it
to vary from point to point even if it
stays in the track here there'll be a
cost in energy of having it change from
point to point so that's the ground
state the ground state is any one of
these possible positions for the field
but always sort of locked
together again again spontaneous
symmetry breaking but this time the
Symmetry is a symmetry of rotation about
here all right now are there domain
walls interesting question in this case
are they domain
walls so let's go back to the gunkan
experiment that we might imagine to
check whether there were domain
walls we
take a big
sample and and one place in the sample
we put the field at this point over here
I don't know let's just call it a and at
the other end we put it at B so along
here the field lies in the a direction
along here it lies in the B
Direction what do you think the ground
state the state of lowest energy subject
to this constraint is is it the the
field is uniform until it gets to some
point and then makes a rapid transition
to the other value the answer is no
that's not the preferred energy
configuration and the reason is that
cost a good deal of energy because uh
making the transition from A to B
suddenly has the effect of making the
gradient terms in the energy
large a much cheaper thing to do is to
have the field gradually vary from here
to here this was not an option in the
case where the Symmetry was just a
reflection uh symmetry but now we have
the option of going smoothly from A to B
so the field at one end of space is at a
and gradually as we move across space it
varies staying in the track here staying
in the track so that it never costs us
much potential
energy and as long there is a
concept Which Way r so there are two
possible ways to go that's right there
are two possible way so let's resolve
that by not putting this at point B
let's put it over here let's just to
resolve that ambiguity but you're right
there is an ambiguity about which way
you go from one point to
another uh if if this point is over here
not at the extreme diametrically
opposite point it will pay to go this
way and not go around the long way
because the field gradient will be
less
yeah if if it was over here you could
get it trapped the other way but given a
pair of points A and B unless you have
this very singular situation where
they're exactly diametrically opposed
there will be a particular uh best state
but it will be a state with smooth
variation from one end to the
other another
words
effectively there's a a a field in this
system for which it does not cost much
energy to vary smoothly from one place
to
another uh the energy cost in having a
gradient that's all there is only the
energy cost in having a gradient and
nothing
else a field with that
character not F itself but we'll we'll
discuss what field it is a field of that
character that uh with this only only
gradient energy
is massless it corresponds to a massless
particle yeah would there in fact the
other paths that you could go that that
might even be
lower by because by by giving a little
bit of of the going away from that a
little bit you might be able to get to
be a little bit
shorter uh okay so it is a theorem this
this you can prove that the way to go
from a to be in the minimum energy is to
have this angle veryy linearly from one
side to another that's not hard to prove
you should not change
the
yeah and not going away from the ground
state just change the angle linearly
yeah that uh that's a theorem you can
prove not too hard to
prove so that is that uh and how do you
prove it you prove it by using um uh
some uh
calculus of variation type minimization
you prove the answer is
linear um at this point uh we don't have
any uh it's minimum all the way around
it's not tilted yeah yeah we have not
tilted the
potential you could imagine an explicit
symmetry breaking which would correspond
to tilting the potential a little bit
right if you tilted it then one point
would be preferred relative to the other
and it would be the ground state right
okay let's uh let's
discuss from the point of view of wave
equations I just want to remind you that
from the point of view of wave
equations
uh a field with only gradient terms in
its energy is massless what does it mean
that it's
massless
um it means that the Quant associated
with it a massless but it also means if
you imagined a wave a wave of wave
number K in other words a wave which
looked like e to the I KX going from one
point to another just a single field now
forget let's forget this complex field
for a minute just a field which goes
like e to the I
KX
uh then we would say that it has a
momentum K it has a momentum k k is
related to The Wave number it has a
momentum
K and if the energy in that field goes
to zero as K goes to
zero that means that the quanta of that
field have zero energy when the momentum
goes to
zero right K is like momentum if the
energy stored in a field with k equals z
vanishes then that says there's no
energy for a particle of very very low
wavelength a very very long wavelength
excuse me very low wave number so uh and
that would correspond to saying a
particle at rest would have no energy if
a particle at rest has no energy it's
called a massless
particle uh so if the energy of a
wave gets lower and lower as the wave
gets longer and longer wavelength in
other words as it varies more and more
smoothly then you call that a massless
particle that's a that's the case of a
massless
particle
um okay so
let's let's look at various potentials
let's start first of all with a
potential which looks like this m^2 over
2 5^ SAR or F star five it doesn't
matter um it's clear that if
you created a wave
that varied from place to place no
matter how long that wavelength was as
long as there was variation in the field
away from 5 equals z there's going to be
an appreciable cost of energy why
because any place where the field is not
zero in particular if it's a wave like
this there's going to be a lot of places
where it's not zero and those places are
going to cost
energy
that is the case of a massive particle
that's the case of a particle which has
energy no matter how long the wavelength
of the particle is okay
um if this is
absent then a very very long wavelength
has very small energy the only terms in
the energy come from the gradient terms
and very very long wavelengths have
small gradients the gradients of very
very small when the wavelength gets
small and that's the case of a massless
particle so a term like m^2 5^ 2 is
called a mass term and it represents the
mass of a part we've discussed this
before so I won't go through it in
detail again but let me just show you
how you can think about decomposing in
this case here where the field likes to
lie on this circle here let's go through
a little bit of mathematics and see if
we can identify
uh why there's a massless
particle and what that massless particle
is the massless particle incidentally
just corresponds to a wave where the
field stays in the lowest energy here if
it stays in the lowest energy then the
long wavelength expectations that just
means the field varies gradually from
place to place only an angle and never
creeps out of this uh track here here
that will have lowest very low energy
and will correspond to something
massless but let's see if we can see
some mathematics for it um how we doing
yeah so let's take the potential to be
derivative of let's take the the lran to
be derivative of f times the derivative
of f
star minus V of f Star
and now let's represent the field in a
new way not by the real and imaginary
part of the field but let's
write
f is equal to row * e to the I
Alpha what is alpha alpha is the angle
on the complex plane row is the radial
value of the field in other words the
magnitude of the field and Al is the
angle row and Alpha are also Fields row
and Alpha can vary from place to place
and let's rewrite the lunian in terms of
row and Alpha now notice Alpha this is
Alpha not fine
notice moving around on the track here
corresponds to keeping row constant and
varying Alpha so you can think of alpha
as a field which whose value is on this
circle here if you like or at least it
has to do with an angle row is a field
which when you change it changes the
potential energy and pushes you away
from the uh from the r from the minimum
energy okay let's let's try to write
down what the lran is in terms of row
and Alpha very easy the derivative of fi
with respect to any direction in space
or in space time the derivative of f is
equal to the derivative of
row time e to the I
Alpha let's differentiating this Factor
leaving this one alone and then the
other term is plus row time the
derivative of e to the I Alpha what's
that
H did I leave out H sorry I should have
put row here D sorry what am I WR
derivative derivative of row
thank you derivative of row * e to the I
Alpha plus row * the derivative of e to
the I Alpha and that's
I
row uh times the derivative of
alpha all time e to the I
Alpha let's factor out e to the I Alpha
and put it on the
outside okay so that's the derivative of
what about the derivative of f star
let's multiply let's work that out
derivative of five star that's exactly
the same thing except with a minus sign
over
here derivative of row minus I row
derivative of
alpha time e to Theus I
Alpha now what happens when we multiply
these two when we multiply these two the
cross term goes away and we just get two
terms one of them is just the derivative
of row squared the e to the I Alpha
cancels the e to the minus I Alpha here
so that you could just dispense with
from the beginning E to the I Alpha goes
away and uh what do we get we get the
derivative of row
squared okay and then we get
plus row
2ar times the derivative of
alpha
squared and then
finally V of what is f star five in
terms of row and
Alpha row squar notice that the
potential only depends on row and not
Alpha that's just the
Symmetry well now let's
say that uh that the very very low
energy
excitations the very very low energy
excitations the very very long
wavelength configurations where the
field varies slowly from point to point
where it stays down in the track here
number one and number two where it very
slowly if we only have we don't have
much energy we're just trying to make a
very low energy excitation it's not
going to pay us to uh to change row very
much we want to keep row right on the
track here so in some approximation
where we don't ever excite any motion up
and down or away from the track here we
can just think of row as a
constant row doesn't vary from point to
point and therefore we can say that row
is what did we call row we called it the
row at the minimum F so we can just
replace this by
f^2 derivative of alha
squ and then the rest of it has only to
do with row has to do with variations of
row from place to place climbing up and
down this well for example and also
potential energies that have to do with
the value of
row the potential energy is going to say
hey don't get far from this point F but
still it's
there this term what does that term look
like that term just looks
like the lran of a field with no
potential at all what about this F what
do we do with this F it's just a number
remember it's just a number it's fixed
it doesn't vary from place to place we
can absorb it into the definition
redefinition of alpha we can say let f f
time Alpha be a new field what can we
call it we call it beta and this would
just become the derivative of beta
squared that would be characteristic of
a field with no Mass
s all right so the F here that's that's
unimportant it can as I said it can be
absorbed in here and just change the
definition from alpha to F time Alpha
since it's a constant and this just
becomes the lran for a massless field
with no potential energy at
all right what is the meaning of that
the meaning of that is if all you're
allowed to do is vary the angle here
then excitations of that type behave
like massless Fields behave like Fields
whose quanta have no masses now on the
other hand what about row row is an
independent
field it's an independent field that has
a lran derivative of row squar and a
term V of
row supposing We Choose the ground state
to be over here at this point remember
we could choose the ground state to be
in any direction then we can move in two
directions we can move around the circle
that's just exciting Alpha we've already
taken care of that that's just a
massless
excitation that uh that costs no energy
except for the gradient terms but we
could also move radially outward what
would happen if we started the field
over here radially
outward and then
what no no let's not give it any uh any
rotation uh yeah it would just oscillate
about this point
it would oscillate about this point in
very much the same way as the field
would oscillate about the origin if
there was a festar f term that
corresponds to a mass oscillations if
you take the field everywhere and
displace it it will just oscillate back
and forth that corresponds to a mass in
other words this V of row here which
could contain for example a row squared
or it could contain a a term which
oscillates about here that does
correspond to a
mass what what a mass is is it's an
energy that's associated with zero
momentum zero momentum means that the
field is homogeneous and doesn't vary
from point to point zero momentum means
no variation at all so if there's energy
stored in a w and a not a w it's not
hardly a wave if there's energy stored
in a configuration where you move every
everybody
simultaneously then it would and it just
rocks back and forth that frequency the
frequency of its motion is the mass all
right so if you took the field
everywhere and you displaced it up onto
the side of the potential it would start
to oscillate everywhere would correspond
to a mass on the other hand if you
displaced it along the track here
nothing much happens if you displaced it
everywhere along the track it would
there would be no restoring Force the
restoring Force
which gives a periodic oscillation
motion that is what a massive field does
it oscillates if you excited
homogeneously and U okay whenever you
have a symmetry and the Symmetry is sp
whenever you have a continuous symmetry
in this case The Continuous symmetry is
a rotation symmetry around here and that
symmetry is spontaneously
broken there is always the
possibility of changing the orientation
of things very gradually from place to
place if you have a continuous Symmetry
and in that case you have massless
excitations massless particles those
particles are called Goldstone
bons Goldstone Bon is a
particle or a field gold stone field is
a field which is massless which has no
restoring in force by virtue of a
symmetry by virtue of the fact that
you're moving the field in a direction
that costs no
energy right so whenever you have a
spontaneously broken symmetry there are
gold stone boson there are gold stone
BOS well there are Goldstone bosons
let's leave it at that in this case the
gold stone Bon is or the Quant of the
field Alpha which is just motion along
this track here
that's a very important Concept in
physics it
um it's very important in particle
physics gives rise to massless particles
we which we'll see uh are really
unwanted in the sense and it's also a
very important uh Concept in condensed
matter physics in condensed matter
physics for example
ferromagnets which like to line up can
be if a ferromagnet where uh where you
can Orient the magnets in any direction
with there's a symmetry on the rotation
there are spin waves spin waves are
gradual variations of the direction of
spin from point to point
gradual and for the same reason that
I've described here a very gradual
variation of the direction of spin from
place to place is not costly in energy
cost almost no energy and those spin
waves behave like massless
particles so the phenomena or the idea
of Goldstone bosons is a really
important Concept in field Theory and
convinced
metaphysics uh where else does it
appear
um all kinds of places is there any
physics which isn't either fuel Theory
or condensed
metaphysics in general relativity uh it
also appears but uh it won't
night uh a long elastic
string is an exam uh with the Motions
the waves on a long a long string let's
just take it not a not a string of
string theory just a you know a long
rubber string from one place to the next
long uh that's an example of a gold
stone Bon or a gold stone field what
would be the Symmetry associated with it
can you guess I I'll set up I'll set up
an example for you
uh forget gravity gravity is not
important here let's suppose there's a
pole over
here another pole over
here a ring around this pole with a
string connected to it and uh and a ring
around here the reason I've set it up in
this way is so that you can move the
whole thing up and down uh uh like that
okay we we know that if we make this
very very very long
there are massless waves which propagate
up and down it massless means they cost
very little energy only gradient energy
can you guess what the Symmetry in this
case
is translation up and down right uh as I
said imagine no gravitational field it
costs no energy to move this whole thing
up or down so it's a symmetry it's
translation symmetry just translation
symmetry up and down
so first of all there's a symmetry next
you can imagine changing the orientation
and not orientation but position
gradually as you go from point to point
this Goldstone B on idea where you do
where you imagine a little symmetry
transformation but a gradual change from
one point to another what would that
look like that would just look like a
very slow variation of the uh of the
vertical position
so an overall motion up and down costs
no energy and a very small variation
across here will also cost very little
energy and the waves the long
wavelengths which propagate up and down
a very very long string are also
Goldstone bosons they're Goldstone
bosons of the symmetry of
translation spin waves are Goldstone
bosons of rotational
symmetry
okay and
uh this field is the gold stone Bon of a
U1
symmetry of the U1 symmetry
here well if the thing was standing
still it has no momentum
itation and oh you you want to give it
some oscillation
energy be careful be careful what you
mean about
momentum you're speaking about vertical
momentum yeah yeah um overall vertical
yeah we could certainly make it have
zero vertical momentum but what about
horizontal
momentum yeah well no there's there's
waves there's waves with with wave
numbers so it's actually if you had the
standing wave it would be a linear
superposition of plus momentum and minus
momentum so what I would mean by
momentum in this case would not be the
vertical momentum but the momentum along
the wave along the uh along the wave
axis the vertical Direction here is just
a stand in for some internal uh
symmetry um
good another example
another example a
slinky let's say you pin down the slinky
at two ends everybody know what a slinky
is yeah you know what a slinky
is you can move the whole Slinky horiz
horizontally doesn't cost any energy
right so there's a symmetry of of
horizontal just think of it as being
infinite long for all practical purposes
then if you move it horizontally costs
no energy so there's a symmetry in this
case it's a horizontal motion on the
other hand you can imagine slowly
varying from place to place how much you
translated it and in that case you would
make a
wave tighter over here less tight over
here but if you do it slowly
enough then this then the uh then the
wave will not cost you much energy if
you do it slowly enough from place to
place if there are no big gradients it
won't cost you much energy so in this
case the Symmetry would be translation
horizontally and uh the waves on a
slinky Al also sound waves are also gold
stone bons they also correspond to
translation of all the
molecules if you have a sample a system
with a in infite system with lots of
molecules and you translate all the
molecules it cost you no energy but if
you translate them a little differently
over here than over here than over here
that creates a very long wavelength
pressure wave or density wave those are
also gold stone
bosons and they all have the character
that they cost no energy when the
wavelength goes to infinity or when the
momentum goes to zero and we call them
massless okay so we've seen some
connections now between symmetries and
massless bons called guge
bons Goldstone bons Goldstone bans I'm
sorry that
I I was apologizing to my friend
Goldstone who was a friend of
mine I called him Gage by
mistake sorry
Jeffrey now anybody instantly fails this
course if they say gu
gou now let's talk about a totally
different subject also connected with
uan symmetry like this so it's not
totally uh disconnected let's talk about
gaug inv variance I'm not sure we'll put
the two concepts together tonight it may
take till next
week another concept called gaug
variance also associated with this U1
symmetry remember that U1 symmetry
symmetry under this kind of operation is
what we identified earlier in past
lectures with electric charge
conservation it doesn't have to be
electric charge but let's think about
electric charge we're going to wind up
with Gauge bons with mass well the real
Photon doesn't have a mass but we could
be thinking about some other gauge Bon
like the Z boson which does have a Mass
for so for the moment I'll just call the
charge electric charge but it might not
be electric charge it might be something
um of a different character and we're
thinking about something which is not
really electric charge but we did
identify the symmetry of this
type with the conservation of the
electric charge carried by the quanta of
the F field
charges of various kinds are always
carried by fields which are
complex and the conservation law is
associated with the Symmetry the
Symmetry is associated with the
U transformation namely multiplication
by a phase okay we've talked about this
at length previous time so we won't go
into it again but
um let's uh
let's AR racee this squiggles
here I'll leave this up because we'll
use it again and
uh this is the Symmetry that we're
interested in five goes to F
Prime now
question must we in must we require in
order for it to be a symmetry must we
require that Theta is constant over
space are we allowed to make
Transformations where Theta can vary
from place to place not uh Theta yeah
Theta are we allowed to imagine
Transformations
where the Symmetry parameter
Theta right now Theta is not a field now
it's just a symmetry parameter where it
is allowed to vary from place to place
in other words where we rotate the phase
of a field differently in some places
than others
is that a symmetry so let's find out
let's find out by doing such an
operation and seeing whether it changes
the L grangian or not that's the test if
you think something might be a symmetry
Try It Out by applying it to the fields
and then stick them back into the lran
and see if the lran changes okay so
here's our transformation F Prime is
equal to e to the I Theta of X where X
could be space or time space and time in
General
SpaceTime let's write
it running out of ink
again let's try
blue ah
good okay so here's our symmetry
operation Let's uh let's calculate the
lran uh let's calculate all right let's
let's first calculate remember what goes
into lran what goes into the L grangian
is the squares of some derivatives and
maybe some potential energy so let's
start with derivatives the
derivative uh arbitrary Direction it
doesn't matter what direction pick a
direction space or time and calculate
the derivative of f Prime here's F Prime
right well first of all it will contain
e to the I Theta time the derivative of
f right the unmodified the before the
transformation takes place and then
it'll contain a second term and that
second term will be F I F derivative of
theta with respect to
X time e to the I Theta
in fact let's Factor e to the I Theta
out it's an overall
multiplicative Factor notice there are
two terms one of them did I write this
correctly I think I did yeah one of them
doesn't care one way or the other
whether Theta varied with respect to X
or not that was this term
here the other term actually involves
the variation from point to point of
theta
okay now let's write the lran as we
might think of it in terms of f prime it
contains we know F Prime we're
interested in derivative of f
Prime uh derivative of f star
Prime oh let's write the let's write the
the derivative of the the conjugate the
derivative of f Prime
Star that's just derivative F
star minus i f
star derivative of theta with respect to
X time e to Theus I Theta now what we're
going to do is we're going to multiply
these
two and see if it's the same as just
multiplying the original derivatives of
five and F star well obviously the
answer is no because there are some
extra terms here but let's see what they
are let's just check first of of all the
e to the I thetas will cancel out so
when I multiply the derivative of f
Prime Times the derivative of five Prime
Star at least these factors will cancel
out in other words the factors will
cancel out if F if Theta doesn't depend
on position if Theta didn't depend on
position then these would cancel out so
let's just erase them uh well I'm not
going to erase them I I don't want to
write the wrong equations so I'll leave
them up there but when I multiply these
together I'm going to
get well actually this is all I was
hoping to get I was hoping to get the
original lran back and show that the
lran is invariant but it's not there's a
couple of extra terms first of all
there's a term
I let's see what there is I fi defi star
minus F star
D this is not zero this is five
derivative of f star this is f star time
the derivative of five this is not zero
time D Theta by
DX that's new I didn't want that there
and then finally there's the squared
term which is five star
five F star 5times derivative of theta
with respect to x²
squared well that's a disaster I mean
it's a disaster if we were hoping that
this would be a a symmetry it's not a
symmetry the new L grangian when
expressed in terms of the the the L
grangian when expressed in terms of f
Prime is not the same as the L grangian
one expressed in terms of
fi what about the potential energy if
the potential
energy is a function only
of f star
five then F star five will not change
when we do one of these symmetry
Transformations even if it depends on
space so V the potential energy that's
symmetric but the kinetic energy the
derivative terms in the energy are not
symmetric and if we trace it down we see
what the problem is the problem is
simply associated with the fact that the
derivative of f Prime is not the same as
the derivative of f well let's go to the
upper
equation even if we ignore the C to the
I Theta that does cancel even if we
ignore that the derivative of f Prime
contains this extra term so we just
don't have a
symmetry
okay well can we do anything to restore
the Symmetry is there anything we can do
lran through well yes of course we could
just throw away these terms in l
grangian
that would not be a very interesting L
grangian with just the potential has no
interesting Dynamics
whatever all right the answer is yes but
to do so you have to introduce more
fields and the additional fields are the
gauge Bon fields in this case if we were
really talking about electromagnetism it
would be the electromagnetic field all
right so let's introduce the
electromagnetic field incidentally a
transformation like this which depends
on
position just a a symmetry A hoped for
symmetry transformation which depends on
position like this is called a gauge
symmetry I do actually I do know where
the term came from but it's a historical
uh
uh uh glitch
it doesn't have to do with uh Tire
gauges or anything like
that
um it's not important where it came from
the the term but that's called a gauge
symmetry gauge symmetry implies that the
Symmetry parameter can be chosen to vary
from place to place now remember Theta
is not itself a field it's just a
generalized symmetry parameter which is
now allowed to vary from place to
place what's actually happening here is
when we make the phase of the field vary
from place to place we're picking up a a
little bit of gradient energy the
gradients are uh changing a little bit
on us and so we're picking up some
gradient energy that wasn't there before
that's all okay let's uh let's can I in
the example you had before of the of the
parabola and like that would that be
like where you had the circle that was
in a constant altitude would that be
like there was bumps in that Circle that
went up and down no no no it's just a
radi it's just it's just if we make a
configuration where the field where the
phase of the field IES from place to
place it costs energy that's all yeah
that's all that's all that's happening
here but I've been very explicit about
it and I've identified this as the
villain in the problem here this term
here right so the question is can we
find some clever way to cancel that out
now why should we want to do
that
uh ultimately it's an experimental fact
that um that all of the interactions of
nature are associated with g symmetries
like this or not all the interactions
but all the gauge symmetries all the
gauge interactions photons z bosons w
bosons all are associated with
symmetries not just of the kind where
you can rigidly everywhere do the
Symmetry transformation but symmetries
where you gradual well it doesn't even
have to be gradual where you an
arbitrary uh variation of the Symmetry
parameters from place to
place okay so let's uh let's say what's
the ingredient that you have to add you
have to add a new collection of fields
in this case just one new field or I
should say four new Fields one for each
direction of space you must add a four
Vector of fields and that four Vector is
If This Were electrodynamics would just
be the vector potential the vector
potential am
mu four Vector potential out of which
you build the electromagnetic field I'll
just remind you quickly what the
connection
is uh the electric field well first of
all the time component of a is the
electrostatic potential it's gradient in
space is the electric field the space
components of a form a three vector and
the curl of that three Vector is the
magnetic field I won't bother writing it
down this is is the standard Vector
potential out of which you build the
electromagnetic field tensor composed of
electric and magnetic fields we'll come
back to that but let's add in to the
Symmetry operation we now ask when you
add a new field and you're interested in
a symmetry you always are have to
address the question how does this new
field
transform when you do the Symmetry
operation in other words if we do the Sy
operation that takes us from 5 to 5
Prime is there also something that we
have to do to a to take us from
a to a prime and the answer is
yes because the justification for this
is the result in the end that you can
keep gaug inv variance but what you do
to a is you just add to
it the derivative mu of theta
in other words the transformation
property of a is not some multiplication
by a phase of a but just adding to a the
gradient of theta a is a four Vector the
derivative of theta is also a four
Vector that's the
operation okay that uh that uh will
allow us to have a symmetry next we have
to change the definition of the L
grangian and the definition of the L
grangian is the new definition of the L
grangian will be to replace ordinary
derivatives by a new kind of derivative
that's called the covariant
derivative it's not got it's not the
covariant derivative of uh of general
relativity it's the covariant derivative
of a gauge Theory and let me let me
Define it for you define d
mu
on five
a covariant derivative of the charged
scalar
field or let's uh yes the covariant
derivative is defined to
be the ordinary
derivative we can take away these M's if
we want it wouldn't but that's all right
leave them
plus get the sign straight
plus
I a mu *
5 definition that's the definition of
the covariant derivative if you like you
can just think of it as a
replacement of derivative by derivative
+
I * a now that may not mean that really
doesn't mean anything by itself it's
something which acts on a Charged field
field this is definition of the
covariant
derivative same thing or the analogous
thing for D muf
star it's equal to D mu F
star now
minus minus I a mu F
star keep in mind this wouldn't make any
sense if F was a real valued field why
not
because if F was a real valued field we
wouldn't want to add something imaginary
but f is itself a complex field and so
adding something additional complex
that's fine no problem okay this is the
definition of the covariant
derivative and the kinetic terms in the
lran forget the forget the potential
terms for a minute the kinetic terms in
the lran are just replaced by the square
or D mu f * D mu F star are and let me
show you why that is gauge invariant why
that now has the invariance that was
lost over
here how this extra little trick of
inventing an extra
field giving it a transformation
property
now telian which did not have this gaug
in variance and makes it gaug invariant
we don't even have to work out the lran
it's enough just to look at the
covariant
derivatives let's
prove let's find the connection here's F
and F Prime where is f and f Prime
here's F and F
Prime let's calculate the covariant
derivative of f
derivative of f Prime and what we want
to
show is that the covariant derivative of
f Prime is essentially the same as the
covariant derivative of
fi that would then establish that the
new lran which involved the square of
these was really invariant so let's
check that out let's
calculate let's recalculate a covariant
derivative of f Prime
that's equal
to first of all the first term is just
the ordinary derivative of Pi Prime and
there it is up
there derivative of I plus I
F derivative of theta with respect to X
I wonder if I have the sign wrong
someplace
um I may have a sign wrong here
uh let's see I think we can fix the
sign by changing the sign over
uh I think over
here if it comes out wrong we'll change
it back again um okay now that's the
first term in the covariant derivative
of f Prime just just the derivative of f
Prime but then we have to
add plus
I something times F
Prime what do I want to put over here
a a
prime a prime because I'm
calculating the covariant derivative of
the primed Fields so I want to put there
a prime all right so let's put a prime
in what is a prime a prime is a
mu
minus
uh D mu
Theta uh D mu Theta times H sorry this
is f
prime a mu minus D mu Theta all
times five Prime is that right I think
that's
right uh
five and um I must have left an out an
overall
phase
um yeah both of them have a factor of e
to the I
Theta now you look at it here was this
extra nasty term which destroyed the
invariance of this expression right but
here is exactly the opp the exactly the
same term but with an opposite sign one
term coming from the transformation of
the derivatives of theta and the other
term coming from the transformation of a
notice they're exact the same I hope I
here we have
i e to the I Theta and D Theta by DX
that's d d uh d d
Theta let's get rid of all the
M yeah so this term and this term just
derivative of
theta this term and this term are
exactly the same they
cancel we succeeded in canceling out or
or um playing off the transformation
properties of the derivative with the
transformation properties of a and
causing the extra term to
cancel so what do we find we find that
derivative or covariant derivative of f
Prime is exactly the same as the
covariant derivative of f except for
this Factor e to the I Theta here we
have to put that back
what about the covariant derivative of
the complex
conjugate I Prime
Star that's equal to the covariant
derivative of f
star time eus I
Theta and guess what when we multiply
this by this the e to the I thet is
cancel out and the lunian is gaug
invariant so this a field here was an
invention a device an
invention uh to sort of forcibly make
the lanan be Gage invariant but we had
to invent a transformation property of
the gauge field itself of the vector
potential
itself okay now
next we're missing something in the
lran what are we
missing oh yes of course we are missing
the potential let's let's add that in we
can uh we can multiply this by this and
get
yeah D Mu Lan is d muf d mu F
star minus V of f star
F this was gaug invariant to begin with
we don't have to modify that but we are
missing something rather important in a
gauge
Theory no
yeah
um this wouldn't be a very interesting
gauge
Theory without some Dynamics for the
vector potential
itself now the vector potential is
really the thing which out of which you
create the electric and magnetic
fields okay anybody know what the lran
for the electromagnetic field is
is anybody know what the energy for the
electromagnetic field
is E2 plus b s how about the
lran It's e^ s minus B2 e s minus b s
but it can also be represented in terms
of the field tensor so let's write it in
terms of the field
tensor the field tensor is called f muu
and I'll just remind you what it is f
muu is an anti-symmetric
object it's the derivative in the Muth
direction of a new minus the derivative
in the newth direction of a
mu so it's a kind of four-dimensional
curl it's it the diagonal components are
zero F0 0 is zero why is that because
it's d0 a0 * d 0 a0 minus d0 a0 at Z all
of the the diagonal elements are zero
it's
anti-symmetric under muu
interchange and
it's components with one space and one
time what are
they the component of f muu with one
space and one time is the electric
field right it has one space
component and that determines the
direction of the electromagnetic field
and what about the term with um uh space
space
components the magnetic field for
example F
XY is equal to b z where B is the
magnetic field and so forth and cycle it
through so this is the electromagnetic
field
tensor and the standard Dynamics the
Maxwell ordinary Maxwell
Dynamics is determined by a
lran and the lran is just f sared is
just F mu new F mu new raising the
indices is just a couple of sign changes
here and there the lran is e^2 minus B2
the energy is E2 + b^2 but the important
thing is that the lran for the
electromagnetic field is involves
nothing but F muu itself how about f muu
is f muu gaug in variant let's check it
to find out we have to
calculate F muu
Prime well that's just equal to D mu a
prime new minus d new a prime
mu all right but now let's remember did
we erase what a prime is we did a prime
is just equal to a I think it was minus
the derivative of Theta all right so
let's just plug it in this is going to
be derivative mu of a
new uh minus the derivative of mu of the
derivative of new of theta I've just
plugged in
for a prime a and then the derivative
with respect to new of theta what's
going to happen when I put this term in
it's going to subtract derivative new of
a mu and then it's going to add
plus d new D mu of
theta okay but D mu d new Theta is the
same as du new D mu Theta it doesn't
matter which order you differentiate in
this is just the fact that uh the order
of differentiation partial
differentiation is immaterial and so
this
cancels and what do we find we find that
F Prime is the same as F this is f so
the electromagnetic field tensor is Gage
in variant
that means that we can construct a
completely gauge invariant
dynamics of the electromagnetic field
coupled to a field whose quanta are
charged
particles these is this is the field
whose quanta are charged particles what
is it it's D mu this whoops this is
mistake here this is D
mu only these covariant derivatives not
ordinary derivatives a potential and
add plus f s I'll just call it f^2
meaning F muu you know the appropriate
thing e^2 minus b^2 there's some
numerical factors which are conventional
is usually a quarter in front of this
but that's that's not important the
important thing is all terms here are
gauge inv variant so we've discovered
the fact that we can promote
OTE a symmetry like U1 here to a local
symmetry a local symmetry means that we
can locally vary the phase or we can
locally do the operation whatever it is
from point to point and still have the
Symmetry but it's always at the cost of
an extra field an extra Vector potential
field and that Vector potential field
can also be assembled into a
Maxwell uh lran that would determine
Maxwell's equations Maxwell's equations
coupled to charge carrying matter that's
what this
is okay what can we not add let me tell
you what we can't add and still beig gug
in
variant first of all we can't add
potentials which are functions other
than functions of f star fi if they were
functions of just the real part of fi
that would kill the Symmetry but but as
far
as
modifying the electromagnetic field what
we cannot add in is a term like let's
call it m^2 / 2 time a mu a
mu remember the mass term for a boson
field is typically an m^2 * the square
of the
field a mass term for a phot
would be a term like this if we added
this term to the Maxwell Theory here we
would be adding a mass to the photon
however it's forbidden if we want the
theory to be gaug
invariant this is not gauge invariant
this is not the same not equal to m^2 /
2 a prime mu a prime
mu so this is forbidden by Gage in
variance there was no no way by hand to
give the photon a mass that's what this
means the photon is
necessarily
massless if you believe in gaug inv
variance and every physicist believes in
gaug inv variance for a a wide variety
of reasons including mathematical
consistency the theory really breaks
down badly if uh if you tried to do this
all right so the photon can't have a
mass or can
it okay or can it is there
no device here by
which taking this lanan just as it is is
there any trick that we can do to give
the photon a mass I'm going to tell you
right now what it is and we'll do it
next week if we spontaneously break the
U1
Symmetry by making the potential here
have one of these uh shapes like
this so that the field likes to sit over
here that will mean that the U1 symmetry
is spontaneously broken not
explicitly and spontaneous symmetry
breaking that's okay I mean this this
lran is gaug
invariant the spontaneous symmetry
braking will have the effect of giving
the photon a
mass and it will also miraculously
remove the gold stone
bone so the effect of spontaneous
symmetry breaking is twofold it removes
the gold stone Bon that was associated
with slow variations of fi from one
point the phase of f on the one hand and
at the same time gives a mass to the
vector potential it gives a mass to the
photon now the photon real Photon
doesn't have a
mass but the zbo on
does this is called we're going to work
this out next time we'll work we'll work
it through next time and just see how
spontaneous symmetry breaking gives rise
to mass for the gauge bow on that's
called the higs phenomenon and this
would be an example of how the higs
phenomenon gives Mass to a particle
which mathematically you're not allowed
to just put in a mass by
hand right that's the that's the
signature or the the basic idea of the
higs phenomena that there may be deep
mathematical reasons why you cannot just
by hand give a particle of mass but
spontaneous symmetry breaking can do it
anyway
involes not say it again
the that we started with yeah involves
the not the not the Coes so why should
we
accept the fact that only for glarian
derivatives it's invari what I'm telling
you is that if you have some uh pre
well first statement you can create a
lran which is gun
variant okay second statement the
coupling between charge carrying fields
and the electromagnetic potential would
become inconsistent if it were in gauge
I'm not going to try to demonstrate that
it really does become mathematically
inconsistent unless it's gaug
invariant
um so why should you believe what is it
what is the
question the question is no the answer
is that you can construct a gauge
invariant L grangian the result is a
nice consistent mathematical structure a
gauge theory if you try to do anything
else you will wind up with a theory uh
which in quantum mechanics which will
have some Terrible Things it'll have
negative probabilities in it even worse
things and uh but I'm not going to go
through that
gauge invariance is an extremely
fundamental principle in theoretical
physics whether you like it or not and
uh for our purposes I think we just have
to accept it we can also accept it as a
empirical fact that all of the particles
namely photons
zons w+ and W minus
bosons
uh uh nature seems to have chosen the
alians to be exactly Gage in variant
it's a good thing thing because we don't
want negative probabilities in a theory
you Justified it by by saying there's an
additional field yeah and you didn't
start with just a plain thing and keep
it that way you added this new field and
you descri with the uh the we had to add
a new field in order to implement the
Symmetry and that's described using the
coar
Der explanation so that's why I
understand that it's okay to do that
with the new field BEC leg yeah that's
right um but we had to add a new field
to do it without the new field we could
not uh keep uh now this this there's
much deeper mathematics here that I
haven't discussed fiber bundles all
kinds of uh all kinds of interesting
mathematics AMU is technically what a
mathematician we call a connection and
there's all sorts of interesting
mathematics which we are not going to
get
into um all right so let me see if I
understand
say the gaging variance leads us U to
this modification which gives rise to
the Goldstone boson no the Goldstone
bosan was a feature of the
theory without Vector
potentials and without gaug inv variance
what the gold stone ban was the energy
of the gold Stone B on was exactly the
energy of making these VAR variable
phases but now we find that there's a
way of making the variable phases
without a cost in
energy why because the lran is invariant
under those uh gradual change changes of
phase what does that mean that means
there's no cost in energy in this
gradual change of phase no gold stone B
but we'll do that next time we'll do it
next time we'll see that this
lran does not have gold stone bons and
it does have a Mass for the
photon does that have anything to do
with why R meand why Rivers I don't
think not that
well why Rivers Don't flow in a straight
line on a relatively label plane
they I don't think so and and the and
the the link the increase is equal to
five the distance yeah not that I know
of but uh I would not be at all
surprised if somebody has found the
gauge theory of
rivers I don't know of any
connection uh I do know that there are
connections with the emotion and shapes
of
am it also has to do with flow of the
water when it forms edies
yeah well I wouldn't be totally
surprised if there was some connection
but none that I've thought
of for more please visit us at
stanford.edu